Guide to the Saturday Press records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Saturday Press Records,
1975-1996.
Saturday Press (Montclair, N.J.)
1.5 linear ft. (3 document boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
6467565
The records document the Saturday Press, a small press dedicated to publishing the works of female poets over the age of 40. The Saturday Press existed from 1975 to 1995. The collection consists primarily of correspondence between the publisher Charlotte Mandell and the authors, as well as correspondence from contestants for the Eileen W. Barnes Award, which the Saturday Press awarded in 1981, 1984, and 1990.
Historical Note
The Saturday Press, a small press named after a poetry group out of which the press sprang, was founded in 1975 by Charlotte Mandell. Charlotte Mandell began by publishing her first book, an experience which made her realize simultaneously the importance of publishing to a new poet, and that publishing was a task within her grasp. Although technically founded in 1975, the press did not begin formal operations until 1981, when a bequest from Eileen W. Barnes provided funding. Mandell used the bequest to establish the Saturday Press, and simultaneously, the Eileen W. Barnes Award, an award granted to a first-time female poet over 40. The bequest also funded the publication of the Press' first three books; after that ran out, the Press reorganized as a non-profit corporation, and relied upon grants, which supported the organization for the remainder of its existence.
The Saturday Press was located in Montclair, New Jersey, near Mandell's home, where she lived with her husband, Irwin Mandell, the director of Clinical Research at the Columbia University Dental School.
The Eileen W. Barnes award (later known simply as the Barnes Award) was announced in 1981, 1984, and 1990, with the announcement and publication of winners taking place over the following few years in each case. The Award was inspired by Charlotte Mandell's realization that there was a lack of support for older first-time poets, especially women, and she planned the prize as an attempt to garner recognition and prestige for such poets The Barnes Award led to as much recognition of the Press as did its publication of more established poets.
The first Barnes Award competition requested contestants to submit a biography along with their poetry submission, and the judges of the first competition clearly found these biographies almost as compelling as the poetry itself. Charlotte Mandell cited them extensively in a talk she presented at Rutgers in 1984, and Rachel Hadas, another Barnes Award judge, wrote an article on the subject of the biographies. The first Barnes Award carried a cash prize of $100 for the winning poet; later awards had no cash prize.
The Saturday Press first published the winner of the first Barnes Award, Ghita Orth, in 1982. In 1983, it also published the runner-up, Annaliese Wagner's book, Hand Work, as well as an anthology of 53 of the contestants, titled Saturday's Women. The Press went on to publish poets such as Jean Hollander, Janice Thaddeus, Anne Nicodemus, Geraldine C. Little, and Gilette Inez. In total, the Saturday Press published 13 books and an audio tape of Charlotte Mandell reading her poem-novella, The Life of Mary. A small press, books were distributed only to local bookstores and authors were largely responsible for their own publicity. Many of the authors, in explaining their choice to publish with the Saturday Press, cited Charlotte Mandell's personal involvement in the editing process, and deep investment in the quality of the final product. The press ceased operations in 1995.
Scope and Content
The collection primarily consists of correspondence and publicity conducted by the Saturday Press: correspondence between the publisher Charlotte Mandell and the authors; correspondence relating to the Eileen W. Barnes Award, including contestant biographies; records of events that publicized the press, such as talks at universities and poetry readings; and clippings of articles citing the press, as well as reader responses to these articles. Finally, the collection contains the entire press run, 13 titles and an audio cassette, as well as photographs and negatives of these books.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into five series:
Series I: Correspondence with Authors, 1981-1996
Series II: The Eileen W. Barnes Award, 1981-1990
Series III: Publicity, 1981-1993
Series IV: Visual Materials, undated
Series V: Publications, 1975-1993
Subjects
Saturday Press (Montclair, N.J.); Hollander, Jean, 1928-; Little, Geraldine Clinton.; Mandell, Charlotte.; Orth, Ghita, 1936-; Thaddeus, Janice Farrar, 1933-; Wagner, Anneliese, 1929-; Eileen W. Barnes award.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
The records were a gift from Charlotte Mandel in 1998.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Correspondence with Authors, 1981 - 1996
  Series I contains the Saturday Press’ correspondence with its authors. This section is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, and chronologically within each folder.
  - Carpenter, Anne, 1984-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hollander, Jean, 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Inez, Collette, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Little, Geraldine, 1982-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Orth, Ghita, 1981-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Partridge, Dixie, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Radin, Doris, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Thaddeus, Janice, 1984-1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Wagner, Anneliese, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Remainder Letters, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II: The Eileen W. Barnes Award, 1981-1990
  This series consists of materials relating to the Eileen W. Barnes Poetry Award, which was given three times by the Saturday Press, in 1982, 1986, and 1990. The materials include contestants’ biographies, which they submitted as part of their application in 1982, correspondence between the judges during the 1986 competition, and announcements of the competitions in 1986 and 1990. The correspondence is arranged chronologically, and the biographies are arranged alphabetically by poet and chronologically within each poet’s file.
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Biographies A-H, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Biographies I-Z, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series III: Publicity, 1981-1993
  This series comprises clippings from articles concerning the Saturday Press, records of promotional events such as poetry readings, transcripts of talks given by Charlotte Mandell on various occasions, and correspondence with distinguished poets for the purpose of collecting “blurbs” to be published on the Press’ books.
  - Correspondence, "Blurb," 1982-1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Grant, 1985-1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Manhattan Theater Club Event, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Poets and Writers' Magazine Article, 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Promotional Materials, 1983-1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Reviews, 1981-1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Talks, 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Student Comments, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Visual Materials, undated
  This series consists of photographs and negatives of Saturday Press books.
  - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series V: Publications, 1975-1993
  This series contains the full press run of the Saturday Press; 13 books of poetry and one audio cassette of the author’s reading of one of the books (Charlotte Mandel’s The Life of Mary). The books are arranged chronologically.
  - Letters Stacked to be Mailed, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - A Disc of Clear Water, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Music of What Happens, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Saturday's Women, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Hand Work, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - eight minutes from the sun, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Ma's Ram, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Crushed Into Honey, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Lot's Wife, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Life of Mary, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - A Well-Tuned Harp, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Keeping Him Alive, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - There Are Talismans, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Watermark, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Life of Mary, 1993, (audio cassette recording) (Box 3, Folder 10)